Guide to the John Zeleny Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Zeleny papers
1897-1951
MS 1167
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
Largely reprints of papers by John Zeleny (1897-1945), together with a volume of laboratory notes kept during his attendance at the University of Berlin (1897), biographical information, photographs, and a testimonial book presented to Zeleny upon his retirement in 1940.
Zeleny, John, 1872-1951
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. John Zeleny in 1980.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
John Zeleny was born on March 26, 1872, in Racine, Wisconsin. He received his B.S. degree from the University of Minnesota in 1892, where he taught physics for five years. In 1897 Zeleny went abroad to study, spending six months at the University of Berlin and two years at Cambridge, where he did research work in the Cavendish Laboratory under Sir J. J. Thomson, the physicist. He received his Ph.D. from the University of Minnesota in 1906 and two years later was named head of the physics department.
In 1915 he moved to Yale and served there as chairman of the physics department from 1920-1940. Zeleny retired from Yale in 1940 and died on June 20, 1951.
Scope and Contents
Largely reprints of papers by John Zeleny (1897-1945), together with a volume of laboratory notes kept during his attendance at the University of Berlin (1897), biographical information, photographs, and a testimonial book presented to Zeleny upon his retirement in 1940.
Physics; Science; Educators; Physicists; Zeleny, John, 1872-1951; Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Physics Department
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  The John Zeleny Papers contain a number of reprints by Zeleny dating from 1897-1945. Also of interest are a testimonial book presented to Zeleny upon his retirement and photographs of Zeleny and other physicists with whom he worked.
  - Biographical sketches of John, Anthony, and Charles Zeleny; with family genealogy, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lab notes from Berlin, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Place of Physics in the Modern World" [address], 1928 November 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Reprints
    - 1897-1899 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1903-1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1930-1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Invitations, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Obituary notices and eulogy by Alois F. Kovarik, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, 1898-1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Oversize photographs, 1920, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Diplomas, 1892, 1897, 1906, 1915 (Box 2)
  - Testimonial book presented to John Zeleny upon his retirement, 1940 (Box 2)